<?xml version="1.0" encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
        "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<refentry id="combo.conf">

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>combo.conf</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
    <refmiscinfo class="sectdesc">Linux-PAM Manual</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>combo.conf</refname>
    <refpurpose>the login access control table file</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>


  <refsect1 id='combo.conf-description'>
    <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
    <para>
      The <filename>/etc/security/combo.conf</filename> file specifies
      (<replaceable>user/group</replaceable>, <replaceable>host</replaceable>),
      (<replaceable>user/group</replaceable>, <replaceable>network/netmask</replaceable>) or
      (<replaceable>user/group</replaceable>, <replaceable>tty</replaceable>), and 
      time 
      combinations for which a login will be either accepted or refused.
    </para>
    <para>
      When someone logs in, the file <filename>combo.conf</filename> is
      scanned for the first entry that matches the
      (<replaceable>user/group</replaceable>, <replaceable>time</replaceable>, <replaceable>host</replaceable>) or
      (<replaceable>user/group</replaceable>, <replaceable>time</replaceable>, <replaceable>network/netmask</replaceable>)
      combination, or, in case of non-networked logins, the first entry
      that matches the
      (<replaceable>user/group</replaceable>, <replaceable>time</replaceable>, <replaceable>tty</replaceable>)
      combination.  The permissions field of that table entry determines
      whether the login will be accepted or refused.
   </para>

    <para>
      Each line of the login combo control table has four fields separated
      by a ":" character (colon):
    </para>

    <para>
      <replaceable>permission</replaceable>:<replaceable>users/groups</replaceable>:<replaceable>times</replaceable>:<replaceable>origins</replaceable>
    </para>


    <para>
      The first field, the <replaceable>permission</replaceable> field, can be either a
      "<emphasis>+</emphasis>" character (plus) for access granted or a
      "<emphasis>-</emphasis>" character (minus) for access denied.
    </para>

    <para>
      The second field, the
      <replaceable>users</replaceable>/<replaceable>group</replaceable>
      field, should be a list of one or more login names, group names, or
      <emphasis>ALL</emphasis> (which always matches). To differentiate
      user entries from group entries, group entries should be written
      with brackets, e.g. <emphasis>(group)</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
      The third field, the <replaceable>times</replaceable> field, is
      a time specification as such as is used by the pam_time module.
      This field is used to indicatate the times at which this rule
      applies.  The format here is a logic list of day/time-range
      entries. The days are specified by a sequence of two character
      entries, MoTuSa for example is Monday Tuesday and Saturday.
      Note that repeated days are unset MoMo = no day, and MoWk = all
      weekdays bar Monday. The two character combinations accepted are
      Mo Tu We Th Fr Sa Su Wk Wd Al, the last two being week-end days
      and all 7 days of the week respectively. As a final example,
      AlFr means all days except Friday.
    </para>

    <para>
      Each day/time-range can be prefixed with a '!' to indicate
      "anything but".
      The time-range part is two 24-hour times HHMM, separated by a hyphen,
      indicating the start and finish time (if the finish time is smaller
      than the start time it is deemed to apply on the following day).
      The word <emphasis>ALL</emphasis> can used in this field to mean
      all times.
    </para>


    <para>
      The fourth field, the <replaceable>origins</replaceable>
      field, should be a list of one or more tty names (for non-networked
      logins), host names, domain names (begin with "."), host addresses,
      internet network numbers (end with "."), internet network addresses
      with network mask (where network mask can be a decimal number or an
      internet address also), <emphasis>ALL</emphasis> (which always matches)
      or <emphasis>LOCAL</emphasis>. <emphasis>LOCAL</emphasis>
      keyword matches if and only if the <emphasis>PAM_RHOST</emphasis> is
      not set and &lt;origin&gt; field is thus set from
      <emphasis>PAM_TTY</emphasis> or <emphasis>PAM_SERVICE</emphasis>".
      If supported by the system you can use
      <emphasis>@netgroupname</emphasis> in host or user patterns. The
      <emphasis>@@netgroupname</emphasis> syntax is supported in the user
      pattern only and it makes the local system hostname to be passed
      to the netgroup match call in addition to the user name. This might not
      work correctly on some libc implementations causing the match to
      always fail.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <replaceable>EXCEPT</replaceable> operator makes it possible to
      write very compact rules.
    </para>

    <para>
       If the <option>nodefgroup</option> is not set, the group file
       is searched when a name does not match that of the logged-in
       user. Only groups are matched in which users are explicitly listed.
       However the PAM module does not look at the primary group id of a user.
    </para>


    <para>
      The "<emphasis>#</emphasis>" character at start of line (no space
      at front) can be used to mark this line as a comment line.
    </para>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="combo.conf-examples">
    <title>EXAMPLES</title>
    <para>
      These are some example lines which might be specified in
      <filename>/etc/security/combo.conf</filename>.
    </para>

    <para>
      User <emphasis>root</emphasis> should be allowed to get access
      from hosts which own the IPv4 addresses during weekdays between
      8am and 5pm. This does not mean that the connection have to be a
      IPv4 one, a IPv6 connection from a host with one of this IPv4
      addresses does work, too.
    </para>
    <para>+ : root : Wk0800-1700 : 192.168.200.1 192.168.200.4 192.168.200.9</para>

    <para>
      User <emphasis>root</emphasis> should be able to have access at any time
      from domain <emphasis>foo.bar.org</emphasis> (uses string matching also).
    </para>
    <para>+ : root : ALL : .foo.bar.org</para>

    <para>
      User <emphasis>root</emphasis> should be denied to get access
      from all other sources.
    </para>
    <para>- : root : ALL : ALL</para>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="combo.conf-see_also">
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>
    <para>
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pam_combo</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pam.d</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pam</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="combo.conf-author">
    <title>AUTHORS</title>
    <para>
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>combo.conf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>
      is a slightly modifed version of
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>access.conf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
